Finding aid to the NYU Abu Dhabi Art Gallery Collection AD.RG.016
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
NYU Abu Dhabi Art Gallery Collection
2014 - 2024
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.RG.016
1.88 Linear Feet in 1 half document box and 4 legal size document boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials have been donated from the Art Gallery Team, and have also been acquired by NYUAD community members who have donated copies of exhibition publications, as well as items acquired by NYUAD Library archivists for integration into the University Archives.
Biographical / Historical
Established in 2014, The NYU Abu Dhabi (NYUAD) Art Gallery is the Gulf's first and only university gallery with a program of scholarly and experimental museum exhibitions. The program seeks to map new territories and ideas through presenting exhibitions by internationally established artists, curators, and scholars at its main space. Its auxiliary venue, the Project Space, is an exhibition laboratory for the university community, and for emerging artists and curators. Situated within NYU Abu Dhabi, the community of which hails from over 115 countries, The Art Gallery organizes free public programs and guided tours in conjunction with its groundbreaking exhibitions. It also produces scholarly publications, which are a core part of its curatorial frame and reflect its academic mission. Collectively, with the Gallery's Reading Room, these welcoming, intimate spaces open up artistic opportunities and initiate regional and international dialogue.
The Galleries Department oversees all exhibition activity on campus, including the main gallery (for museum exhibitions), the Project Space (for experimental projects), and the Christo Award (for emerging UAE artists).
From https://www.nyuad-artgallery.org/en_US/about/
Scope and Contents
The NYU Abu Dhabi Art Gallery Collection is an accumulating collection of publications and ephemera by and about the Art Gallery. Primarily comprised of exhibition catalogs and research publications in print, the collection includes a comprehensive set of copies produced for each exhibition. In most cases, this will be an exhibition program, curatorial catalog, youth guide, and any book project associated with the exhibition. Independent book projects also form part of the collection.
Related Materials
Related collections include the NYU Abu Dhabi Arts Center collection, NYUAD Publications and Ephemera, the Woodman Taylor Collection, and the Abby Weed Grey Papers.
- General
  - Ephemera related to art at NYU Abu Dhabi, 2012-2014 (Box 1)
  - General Art Gallery Publications (Box 1)
  - Imagine Science/Arts Center/Art Gallery, 2015-2018 (Box 5)
- Main Gallery
  - On Site, The Inaugural Exhibition, November 1, 2014 - January 17, 2015 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Curated by: Maya Allison
    Featured Artists: Ebtisam Abdulaziz, Tarek Al-Ghoussein, Mohammed Ahmed Ibrahim, Basim Magdy, Rashid Rana, Mary Temple
  - Slavs and Tatars, Mirrors for Princes: Both Sides of the Tongue, February 28 - May 30, 2015 (Box 2)
    Curator: Maya Allison
    Featured Artists: Slavs and Tatars Art Collective
  - Diana Al-Hadid, Phantom Limb, March 6 - May 28, 2016 (Box 2)
    Curators: Maya Allison, Reindert Falkenburg, Alistair Rider, Sara Raza
    Featured Artist: Diana Al-Hadid
  - Invisible Threads: Technology and its Discontents, September 22, 2016 - January 7, 2017 (Box 2)
    Curator: Maya Allison, with Bana Kattan
    Featured Artists: Ai Weiwei, Jamie Allen, Aram Bartholl, Taysir Batniji, Wafaa Bilal, Liu Bolin, Jonah Brucker-Cohen, Heather Dewey-Hagborg, Michael Joaquin Grey, Monira Al Qadiri, Evan Roth, Phillip Stearns, Siebren Versteeg, Addie Wagenknecht, Kenny Wong
  - But We Cannot See Them: Tracing a UAE Art Community, 1988-2008, March 2 - August 26, 2017 (Box 2)
    Featured Artists: Ebtisam Abdulaziz, Jos Clevers, Mohamed Ahmed Ibrahim, Mohammed Kazem, Abdulla Al Saadi, Hassan Sharif, Hussain Sharif, Vivek Vilasini
  - Inventing Downtown: Artist-Run Galleries in New York City, 1952–1965, October 4, 2017 - January 13, 2018 (Box 3)
    Curator: Melissa Rachleff
    Gallery/Project Participants: Tanager Gallery, Hansa Gallery, Brata Gallery City Gallery, Reuben Gallery, Delancey Street Museum, Judson Gallery 112 Chambers Street, 79 Park Place March Group, Judson Church's Hall of Issues, The Center, Spiral Group Green Gallery
  - Permanent Temporariness: Sandi Hilal and Alessandro Petti, February 24 - June 9th, 2018 (Box 3)
    Curators: Salwa Mikdadi and Bana Kattan
    Featured Artists: Sandi Hilal and Alessandro Petti
  - Ways of Seeing, September 3, 2018 - January 5, 2019 (Box 3)
    Curators: Sam Bardaouil and Till Fellrath
    Featured Artists: Ghada Amer, Federic Borgella, James Casebere, David Claerbout, Jojakim Cortis and Adrian Sonderegger, Salvador Dali, Hans-Peter Feldmann, Andreas Gursky, Mona Hatoum, Paul and Marlene Kos, Alicja Kwade, Lateefa bint Maktoum, Gustav Metzger, Shana Moulton, Vik Muniz, Grayson Perry, Michelangelo Pistoletto, Fred Sandback, Markus Schinwald, Hassan Sharif, Cindy Sherman, John Speed, Kim Tschang-Yeul, James Turrell, James Webb
  - ZIMOUN, February 26 – June 1, 2019 (Box 4)
    Featured Artist: Zimoun
  - Speculative Landscapes: Areej Kaoud, Ayman Zedani, Jumairy, Raja'a Khalid, September 16 – December 7, 2019 (Box 4)
    Featured Artists: Areej Kaoud, Ayman Zedani, Jumairy, Raja'a Khalid
  - The Sovereign Forest, January 22-May 30, 2020 (Box 4)
    Featured Artist: Amar Kanwar, in collaboration with Sudhir Pattnaik/Samadrusti and Sherna Dastur
  - not in, of, along, or relating to a line, January 20 - July 10, 2021 (Box 4)
    Curators: Heather Dewey-Hagborg and Maya Allison
    Featured Artists: Addie Wagenknecht, Cao Fei, Eva and Franco Mattes, Lee Blalock, Maryam Al Hamra, micha cárdenas, Ramin Haerizadeh, Rokni Haerizadeh, Hesam Rahmanian, Sophia Al-Maria, Zach Blas
    *described as the Gallery's first ever virtual born-digital virtual exhibition.
  - Modernisms: Iranian, Turkish, and Indian Highlights from NYU's Abby Weed Grey Collection, November 15, 2021 - February 5, 2022 (Box 4)
    Curator: Lynn Gumpert
    Featured Artists: Parviz Tanavoli, Fahrelnissa Zeid, and M.F. Husain (and more)
  - Khaleej Modern: Pioneers and Collectives in the Arabian Peninsula, September 6 - December 11, 2022 (Box 4)
    Curators: Aisha Stoby and Tala Nassar
    Multiple Artists from Bahrain, Kuwait, Oman, Qatar, Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates. See exhibition publication for details.
  - Blane De St. Croix: Horizon, October 3, 2023 - January 14, 2024 (Box 4)
    Featured Artist: Blane De St. Croix
  - In Real Time, February 22 - June 9, 2024 (Box 4)
    Curator: Duygu Demir
    Featured Artists: Moza Almatrooshi, Rana Begum, Chafa Ghaddar, Julie Becton Gillum, Gözde İlkin, Kiori Kawai, Sol LeWitt, Cristiana de Marchi, Ramin Haerizadeh, Rokni Haerizadeh, and Hesam Rahmanian, Haleh Redjaian, (and more).
- The Project Space
  - Project Space, 2015 (Box 5)
  - Project Space, 2016 (Box 5)
  - Project Space, 2017 (Box 5)
  - Project Space, 2018 (Box 5)
  - Project Space, 2019 (Box 5)
  - Project Space, 2020 (Box 5)